Guide to the Bob Fitch Photography Archive M1994
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bob Fitch photography archive
1960-2016
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Fitch, Bob
M1994
83 Linear Feet 139 containers (133 manuscript boxes and 6 flat boxes)
The Bob Fitch Photography Archive consists of the photographic work of activist and photojournalist Bob Fitch, documenting the civil rights movement, the farm worker movement, the peace movement, other social justice movements and issues, cultural change, religion, as well as his professional and personal life.
Scope and Contents
The Bob Fitch Photography Archive primarily consists of photographic materials: contact sheets, negatives, prints, and slides. The images are predominantly black and white, however there are also color images. There is additionally a small amount of notes, correspondence, newspaper clippings, audiovisual materials, and research materials. The collection also contains documents, graphics, spreadsheets, databases, software programs, video, audio, and other material created and/or stored on computers, removable media, and hard drives that were managed by Bob Fitch. The CD-ROMs have been processed and can be accessed but the rest of the computer media is closed until processing has been completed. The collection is composed of Bob Fitch’s work as a photojournalist and activist documenting the leaders and ordinary people involved in social justice, civil rights, labor, and peace movements. The collection also records his professional, personal, and family life. Some of the subjects the materials cover are Cesar Chavez, the United Farm Workers, Dorothy Day, the Catholic Worker movement, Martin Luther King Jr., the Southern Christian Leadership Conference and the civil rights movement, Daniel and Philip Berrigan, David Harris, Joan Baez, hippie communes and communities, and the campaigns of Ron Dellums and other progressive politicians. The collection also documents cultural change, alternative lifestyles, sexuality, art, religion, spirituality, reconciliation movements, nonviolence, ecology, youth, poverty, family life, and living conditions. Fitch work was primarily based in Northern California and the San Francisco Bay Area as well as the American South. Bob Fitch used a numbering system to organize his photographs. The numbers ascend from 101 and are, on a macro level, chronological. Each contact sheet was assigned a number which was marked on the back of the sheet. The negatives were placed in an envelope marked with the same number. Large projects, such as the Glide Foundation, SCLC, and the UFW East Coast trip, had their own numbering system – the initials of the organization followed by a number, again ascending from 101. Fitch arranged the negatives from these large projects with the rest of the materials from that project and they were separated from the main group of negatives. The numbering system, where existent or legible, has been noted in the scope and contents at the file level in this guide. Some materials containing privacy and confidentiality issues have been closed for 80 years from the date it was created. Within this guide, these files will be marked with a Restricted Material note specifying the extent of the closure period.
Biographical
Bob Dewitt Fitch (1939-2016) was an activist, photojournalist, union steward, community organizer, minister, housing program manager, and musician. He was born in Los Angeles, California on July 20, 1939. His father, Robert, was a professor of Christian ethics and a United Church of Christ minister. Bob Fitch’s mother, Marion Weeks Dewitt, was a homemaker. In 1950 the family moved to Berkeley, California, where Fitch became involved with socially committed families of Communist and Socialist organizers, was active in the folk music scene, and interned at the community-supported radio station KPFA. He graduated from Berkeley High School in 1957. In 1961 Bob Fitch graduated from Lewis and Clarke College in Portland, Oregon with a Bachelor's of Science in Psychology and then received a Bachelor's and Master's in Divinity from the Pacific School of Religion in Berkeley, California. While in the seminary Fitch read James Baldwin's The Fire Next Time and had an experience where he felt the need to somehow be artistically involved in portraying the elements emphasized in the book. He settled on photography as the best medium to achieve this goal. Fitch was ordained as a United Church of Christ minister in 1965. After graduating from the Pacific School of Religion Fitch interned with the Glide Foundation in San Francisco, where he was a community organizer working with street gangs, the homeless, hippies, and gay, lesbian, and transsexual groups. The Glide Foundation asked Bob Fitch to do photography for books published by them. Without any formal training in photography, Fitch studied the works of Dorothea Lange and Henri Cartier-Bresson, talked to professional photographers, took free courses on photography, and began documenting the groups he was working with in San Francisco. In 1965 Fitch was invited to be a staff photographer for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference during the civil rights movement. He worked in areas and situations where it was considered to be too dangerous for African-American journalists to operate. His role was to take photographs and file stories, acting as a wire service for national African-American newspapers and magazines. Fitch photographed voter registration, voting, and recruitment and training for African-American political candidates during the first election following the passage of the Voting Rights Act in 1965. He also documented the everyday lives of African-Americans, including marches, demonstrations, meetings, SCLC's organizing efforts in Chicago, Martin Luther King Jr.'s People-to-People tours in Alabama, and the Meredith Mississippi March Against Fear. In 1968 Bob Fitch moved back to Oakland, California where he continued to document and be involved in social justice movements. After Martin Luther King Jr.’s assassination in April 1968, Fitch photographed Coretta Scott King and her family during the funeral and afterwards. Discouraged after attending an interracial retreat on nonviolence in the Santa Cruz Mountains which devolved into divisiveness, a vision of Martin Luther King Jr., appeared to Fitch and told him "Bob! Continue the work!" The next day Fitch made a list of leaders in social justice movements that he admire and respected. He wanted to document them before they too were killed, beaten, or jailed. These activists included David Harris and Joan Baez, Cesar Chavez, Dorothy Day, Daniel and Philip Berrigan, and Pete Seeger. He also sought to document cultural and spiritual movements including hippies, communes and the anti-war movement. Fitch documented political campaigns and local and national politicians including Ron Dellums, Warren Widener, Betty Ann Bruno, Shirley Chisholm, and Andrew Young. He also photographed journalists, photographers, activists, clergy, and artists including: Cornell Capa, Don Devereaux, Betita Martinez, Evan Golder, Robert Olmstead, and Ali Luterman. In his photography he emphasized the role of the rank and file as agents for social change and he was propelled by a desire to not just observe movements but to be deeply involved in them. In 1978 Fitch started working for California’s Department of Housing and Community Development, where he helped develop affordable housing in rural communities. After retiring in 1996 Fitch continued his involvement in social justice movements by working with the Resource Center for Nonviolence in Santa Cruz and travelling to Israel and Palestine, Sri Lanka, Vietnam, Brazil, and Mexico. He also worked for immigrants' rights and for Luis Alejo's campaign for California Assembly. Bob Fitch died of complications from Parkinson's disease on April 29, 2016 in Watsonville, California. Bob Fitch wrote several books, his photographs have been featured in books and in exhibits, including at the Smithsonian Institution.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research except restricted materials which are closed until the date noted at the file level. The majority of audiovisual material in the collection has been digitally reformatted for preservation and materials that are unrestricted are available to view in the Special Collections Reading Room; audiovisual materials not already reformatted are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into 9 series. Series 1: Subject Files, Series 2: Classics, Series 3: Southern Christian Leadership Conference/Coretta Scott King, Series 4: United Farm Workers/United Farm Workers Organizing Committee, Series 5: Glide Foundation/Glide Memorial United Methodist Church, Series 6: Black Star Agency, Series 7: Negatives, Series 8: Business Records, Series 9: Computer Media/Digital Materials. The collection is in original order and the series mostly reflect Bob Fitch’s original titles and organization. Many of the images in Series 2: Classics, Series 6: Black Star Agency, and Series 9: Computer Media/Digital Materials either duplicate, overlap, or complement materials in other series. Additional related images may be found in other series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased; 2013, 2014, and 2015. Accessions 2013-194, 2013-209, 2014-076, 2014-077, 2014-095, 2015-008, and 2015-009. Gift; 2016. Accessions 2016-133 and 2017-052.
Related Materials
Stanford University Libraries created an exhibit from images Bob Fitch selected and digitized. The physical originals of these images can be found in this collection. A portion of Series 9: Computer Media/Digital Materials is composed of these digitized/digital images. The exhibit galleries and catalog can be viewed here: https://exhibits.stanford.edu/fitch There are two additional galleries: Nonviolent Peaceforce in Sri Lanka, 2005 https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/hh188hp7947 Marches, Demonstrations, Social Justice, 1964-2011 https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/nb583sk7324
The contact sheets from the Bob Fitch photography archive have been digitized and can be viewed using this link: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/10257777
Stanford University Libraries has also scanned and digitized a number of books either authored by Bob Fitch or featuring his photographs. The images used in the books can be found in the collection. The books are catalogued as the Bob Fitch Collection and can be viewed using this link: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/catalog?q=%22Bob+Fitch+Collection.%22&search_field=subject_terms Other related materials: 1. The Bob Fitch Photography Archive, Movements for Change, Stanford University Libraries 2. Black Star Collection, Ryerson Image Centre, Ryerson University 3. Daniel and Philip Berrigan Collection, #4602. Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library 4. Dorothy Day – Catholic Worker Collection, Marquette University, Department of Special Collections and University Archives 5. Farmworker Movement Documentation Project, University of California San Diego Library 6. The King Center 7. Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Archive, Howard Gotlieb Archival Research Center at Boston University 8. The Martin Luther King, Jr. Research and Education Institute 9. The Ronald V. Dellums Congressional Papers, African American Museum and Library at Oakland 10. SNCC Legacy Project, Duke University 11. Southern Christian Leadership Conference records, Stuart A. Rose Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library, Emory University 12. United Farm Workers, Walter P. Reuther Library, Wayne State University 13. War Resisters League Records (DG 040), Swarthmore College Peace Collection
African Americans -- Civil rights -- History -- 20th century; African Americans -- History -- 20th century -- Pictorial works; African Americans -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Agricultural laborers -- California -- History -- 20th century; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- Organizing; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States -- 20th century; Catholic Worker Movement; Civil rights demonstrations -- United States; Civil rights movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Civil rights workers -- United States; Communal living -- United States; Conscientious objectors; Demonstrations; Documentary photography; Elections; Hippies -- United States -- Pictorial works; Hispanic American politicians; Immigrants -- Civil rights -- United States; Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States; Mexican Americans; Navajo Indians; Nonviolence; Peace movements -- United States; Photographs; Photographers -- Political activity -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Photographers -- Political activity -- United States -- History -- 21st century; Photography -- United States -- 20th century; Political activists -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Political campaigns -- United States -- History; Protest movements -- United States; Social justice -- United States -- 20th century; Social justice -- United States -- 21st century; United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Civilian relief; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States; war -- Religious aspects -- Catholic Church; United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980 -- Pictorial works; Fitch, Bob; Alejo, Luis, 1974-; American Indian Movement; Baez, Joan; Berrigan, Daniel; Black Panther Party; Chavez, Cesar, 1927-1993; Day, Dorothy, 1897-1980; Dellums, Ronald V., 1935-; Gaskin, Stephen; Glide Foundation of San Francisco; Glide Memorial United Methodist Church (San Francisco, Calif.); Harris, David, 1946-; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Rainbow Family of Living Light; Resource Center for Nonviolence (Santa Cruz, Calif.); Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Southern Christian Leadership Conference.; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); United Farm Workers; United Farm Workers Organizing Committee; Wheeler, William, 1940-; Young, Andrew, 1932-
- Series 1: Subject Files, 1960-2016; 23 Linear Feet 43 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Contains primarily photographic materials: contact sheets, prints, negatives and slides. Additionally there is a small amount of correspondence, newspaper clippings, notes, and audio recordings. This series also contains a small amount of restricted material that is closed until 80 years after the date of creation. Bob Fitch separated some of his most iconic images and these are in the Series 2: Classics. There is also some overlap between images in Series 1: Subject Files and Series 2: Classics. There are also duplicate images in Series 6: Black Star Agency. Additionally Series 9: Computer Media/Digital Files contains digitized copies of some of the images found in Series 1: Subject Files.
  Biographical/Historical
  This series documents the people, organizations and movements that Bob Fitch was involved with or interested in, including: Dorothy Day, Daniel and Philip Berrigan, David Harris, Joan Baez, the peace movement, the Black Panther Party, national and local politicians and political campaigns and Bob Fitch's family and friends. The series also documents cultural change, alternative lifestyles, religion, sexuality, poverty, and youth.
  Arrangement
  Series 1: Subject Files is arranged alphabetically and is primarily in original order.
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research, with the exception of boxes 134, 136 and 137 which are closed for 80 years after the date of creation because of sensitive material related to medical privacy and personal material. The date the materials are restricted to has been noted at the file level.
  - Contact sheet index: 6090-6190, 1960-2016 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology and list of folders, 1960-2016 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Airport bomb threat [contact sheets], 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contact sheets are numbered 2485-2487, 2494.
  - Airport search, La Guardia Airport, New York, New York [contact sheets], January 11, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3618.
  - Aikido [contact sheets], May 30, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contact sheets are numbered 5747, 5748.
  - Alameda Flea Market, Alameda, California [contact sheets], 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3518, 3686, 3687, 4172, 4175, 4191.
  - Alameda High School fire, Alameda, California [contact sheets], March 17, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Sheets are numbered 3691, 3692.
  - Alejo, Luis: Photo identifications and timeline, 2010-2012 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alejo, Luis: Photography exhibit, 2010-2012 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Allen, John [contact sheets], June, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3425.
  - Allen, Linda [prints], 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Prints are numbered 5887, 5888.
  - Allen, Linda [prints], 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Prints are numbered 5912.
  - Allens [prints], 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Prints are numbered 5909.
  - Alternatives, San Francisco, California [contact sheets], 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Contact sheets are numbered 1902, 1903.
  - American Gothic, hippie [copy negatives], 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Medical Association Conference: Exhibit, San Francisco, California [contact sheets], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Contact sheets are numbered 4519, 4520.
  - American Report office [contact sheets], April, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3359, 3362.
  - Amnesty International [contact sheets], 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Contact sheets are numbered 4143-4152, 4178-4185, 4303-4305.
  - Anderson, Craig [contact sheets], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Member of the "Intrepid 4", U.S. Navy sailors who deserted from the USN Intrepid while it was docked in Japan during the Vietnam War. They later sought asylum in Sweden via the Soviet Union. Craig Anderson returned to United States and was briefly imprisoned.
    Contact sheets are numbered 3487-3491.
  - Apartheid march, San Francisco, California [slides], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Archbishop Helder Pessoa Camara [prints], 1960-2016 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ash Wednesday march, San Francisco, California [contact sheets], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3278-3280.
  - Acorn neighborhood redevelopment, Oakland, California [contact sheets], 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Contact sheets are numbered 432, 437, 442, 447.
  - Atlanta - San Francisco [contact sheets], 1966 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Contact sheets are numbered 155, 157-160, 162-165.
  - Atlanta, Georgia [contact sheets], 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Contact sheets are numbered 130, 131, 141, 142, 144-148, 159.
  - Austins-Weaverville [contact sheets], February, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Contact sheets are numbered 1600.
  - Automobile accident, Oakland, California [contact sheets], 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3638, 3639.
  - Automobile junkyard, Oakland, California [contact sheets], 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Contact sheets are numbered 1972, 1974, 2074.
  - Avakian, Spurgeon [contact sheets], 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Alameda County and California Superior Court Judge and Berkeley School Board member. Father of Robert Bruce Avakian.
    Contact sheets are numbered 1957, 1960, 1961.
  - Baer, Morley [contact sheets], August 9, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3920, 3923.
  - Baez, Joan [contact sheets], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Contact sheets are numbered 2917-2919.
  - Baez, Joan: Concert, Oakland, California [contact sheets], August 3, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3812-3818.
  - Baez, Joan: Concert, Oakland, California [slides], 1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bahamas [contact sheets], 1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Contact sheets are numbered 4127.
  - Bahamas: Anglican People in the Bahamas: Slideshow with script, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes an audio reel and audio cassette which were removed and placed in Box 133.
  - Bahamas: Anglican People in the Bahamas: Slideshow audio reel, 1974 (Box 133, Reel 1)
  - Bailey, D'Armey -Simmons, Ira joint campaigns for city council, Berkeley, California [contact sheets], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Contact sheets are numbered 2629, 2642, 2643, 2691, 2692, 2710, 2788, 2789, 2896.
  - Bar-10 Ranch [contact sheets], April 16, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Contact sheets are numbered 5605.
  - Barnes, Peter [contact sheets], October 21, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Contact sheets are numbered 4062, 4063.
  - Barr, Rod, New York, New York [contact sheets], January 11, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3613.
  - Barrett desk [contact sheets], May 15, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3788, 3789.
  - BART Station Group, Oakland, California [contact sheets], March 31, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Contact sheets are numbered 4170, 4171.
  - Bay Area Rapid Transit [BART] [contact sheets], 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Contact sheets are numbered 549-557, 631-636.
  - Beast Street Theater, Alameda, California [contact sheets], June, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3424.
  - Beggs, Edward and family [contact sheets], June, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3472-3475.
  - Bennett, Hal, Linda and Aaron [contact sheets], 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Contact sheets are numbered 2888, 2889, 3336, 3337.
  - Bennett, Hal and Aaron [contact sheets], September, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3410.
  - Berkeley City Council, Berkeley, California [contact sheets], July, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Contact sheets are numbered 2892.
  - Berkeley elections, Berkeley, California [contact sheets], April, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3744-3746.
  - Berkeley: Miscellaneous, Berkeley, California [contact sheets], March, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3680.
  - Berrigan, Daniel: San Francisco Bay Area, California [contact sheets], 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Contact sheets are numbered 677-691, 701, 702.
  - Berrigan, Daniel: Stanford, California [contact sheets], 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Contact sheets are numbered 3388, 3389.
  - Berrigan, Daniel and Philip: Photo identifications, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Berrigan, Daniel and Philip [contact sheets and correspondence], 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Contact sheets are numbered 676, 708, 710, 712, 714, 715, 718, 720, 721, 723, 725, 727, 750, 3440-3451.
  - Berrigan, Daniel and Philip [prints] [part 1 of 2], 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Berrigan, Daniel and Philip [prints] [part 2 of 2], 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Berrigan, Daniel and Philip [slides], 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bicycle race: Nevada City Classic, Nevada City, California [contact sheets], June 17, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bilek [prints], 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bilek family [prints], 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Prints are numbered 5757, 5760, 5762, 5763, 5769-5772, 5776.
  - Bird, Richmond, California [contact sheets], 1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Contact sheet is numbered 2571.
  - Birmingham Civil Rights Institute: T-Shirt, 2013 (Box 132, Item 1)
  - Black Panther Party, Oakland, California [contact sheets], 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)